Finding Aid for the Percival Bailey Personal Collection of Papers and Photographs Biomed.0339
UCLA Library Special Collections
Percival Bailey Personal Collection of Papers and Photographs
1902-1992
UCLA Library Special Collections
Biomed.0339
3 Linear Feet (2 cartons)
Dr. Percival Bailey was an important contributor to many fields of the basic and clinical neurosciences, and a distinguished teacher and author. This is a collection of papers and photographs from Dr. Bailey's home files. Included are documents about his personal life and family, mementos of many, but not nearly all of the many honors and awards that came to him, manuscripts of charming autobiographical essays and his thoughts about psychiatry and psychiatrists. Many aspects of his professional life and his remarkable mentoring of an outstanding group of mid-20th century neurosurgeons emerge from the papers. The photographic record is especially rich in documenting his students and colleagues from around the world.
Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9970515913606533
Acquisition Information
The collection was a 1994 gift from Irene Bailey Freyer to UCLA.
Biography
Dr. Percival Bailey was a renowned and much-honored scientist, clinician, teacher and administrator, who made major contributions in neuropathology, neuroanatomy, neurophysiology, neurosurgery and psychiatry. He was born May 9, 1892 in a small town in the southern tip of Illinois, an area know as Little Egypt. An intelligent and energetic student, determined to escape his hard-scrabble background through education, he worked his way from a one-room elementary school to Southern Illinois State Normal College, and from there to a Ph.D. at the University University of Chicago and a simultaneous M.D. at Northwestern University. Outstanding teachers, especially in anatomy and neurology, aroused his special interest in the nervous system.
After his internship, in 1919 Bailey was accepted to join Harvey Cushing's neurological surgery team at Harvard. This valuable and rewarding, but also difficult, association between the two men continued in an on-and-off fashion until 1928. Bailey spent a year in Boston, then returned to Chicago for a year with the neuropathologist George Boris Hassin, back to Boston, then a year of study with Pierre Marie in Paris in 1921/1922, and back to Boston again. In 1925, now a married man, Bailey returned to Paris and worked with the psychiatrist Henri Claude for a year. Then back to Boston and Cushing for the last time. In 1928 Bailey became the head of the Department of Neurological Surgery of the newly established University of Chicago School of Medicine.
Dr. Bailey remained as Professor of Surgery and Professor of Neurology at the University of Chicago until 1939. Then he joined the University of Illinois as Professor of Neurology and Neurological Surgery until his retirement in 1968. Although his scientific and teaching activities continued, around 1950 diminished eyesight forced a cessation of his surgical and histological work. This provided time to shift some of his attention more to psychiatric study of the nervous system, which had always attracted him, and from 1951 until his retirement in 1967, Dr. Bailey served as Director of the Illinois State Psychopathic Institute and Research and Educational Consultant to the Illinois Department of Public Welfare.
Dr. Bailey died August 11. 1973. This Renaissance Man, who spoke French and German fluently, read widely in philosophy, history, art, and wrote charming essays, was widely beloved and honored. More than 200 neuroscientists and surgeons from around the world, most his former students and colleagues, personally joined in his 60th birthday celebration in Chicago. He was a recipient of several honorary doctorates, including Docteur honoris causa de l'Université de Paris, was named Chevalier de la Légion d'Honeur de France and a chosen a member of the Order of Merit of the Federal Republic of Germany. "A Biographical Memoir" with bibliography by Bailey's pupil, colleague and friend Dr. Paul C. Bucy, published by the National Academy of Sciences, 1989, provides a full account of Dr. Bailey's life and accomplishments.
Scope and Content
This collection, preserved and possibly edited by Yevnigé Bashian Bailey (Mrs. Percival Bailey), provides a enlightening picture of Dr. Bailey as human being, thinker, doer, teacher. Autobiographic and biographic accounts elucidate his life and musings, his interactions with mentors and mentees, his travels; and these accounts are enriched by an extensive photographic record. Not to be found, however, except by indirection, are the records of his scientific and clinical life, his over 260 journal articles, chapters, and books. The collection does include drafts of the chapters of his autobiographical volume "Up from Little Egypt", and drafts of his thoughts about Sigmund Freud and psychoanalysis.
The collection is organized into the following series:
Missing Title
Series 1. Personal Papers, 1912-1978. 27 folders
Series 2. Honors and Awards, 1949-1983. 12 folders
Series 3. Professional and Personal Writings, 1935-1972. 29 folders
Series 4. Professional Life, 1949-1992. 18 folders
Series 5. General Correspondence, 1946-1973. 3 folders
Series 8. Photographs, 1902-1973. 23 folders
Related Material
University of Illinois at Chicago. Health Sciences Library Special Collections: "Unpublished writings of Percival Bailey, 1945-1965". WZ 100 B155u 1945
University of Illinois at Chicago. Health Sciences Library Special Collections: "Percival Bailey Collection", more than 600 rare and important volumes donated by Percival Bailey
Psychiatry -- Archival resources; Neurosurgery -- United States -- Manuscripts; Neuroscientists -- Archival resources; Bailey, Percival
- Personal Papers, 1912-1978; Series 1.; 27 folders
  - Curricula vitae and publications list., circa 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    various editions of the c.v., the latest circa 1963; publications list, 1916-1965; some additional notes
  - Entries for various "Who's Who" publications. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    "Who's Who in World Science", ca. 1939; "American Men & Women in Science, The Medical Sciences", after 1959; "Who Was Who", after 1973
  - Biographical Prelude", by Ruth Anderson Tooze., circa 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    annotated typed draft (photocopy) of the introductory chapter of "Up from Little Egypt", by Percival Bailey
  - Biographical memoranda., circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    typescript drafts: "Biography of Percival Bailey, M.D., Ph.D." (2 p.); "The Essays of Percival Bailey, M.D., Ph.D., 'Up From Little Egypt' " (4 p.)
    General note
    introductory material for publication of Dr. Bailey's volume of reminiscences; presumed author, Paul Bucy
  - Tribute at the Chicago Literary Club, on the publication of "Up from Little Egypt"., circa 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    typed drafts of biographical comments; some notes on the Chicago Literary Club
  - Church and community involvements., 1945-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    the Baileys attended the First Congregational Church, Evanston, Illinois, and also had close connections with the Armenian Church and the Armenian community of Chicago; Dr. Bailey served as Clerk of Election for Cook County for the general election of November 6, 1956
  - Southern Illinois University (formerly Southern Illinois State Normal University)., 1912, 1953-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Dr. Bailey's 1912 Commencement program; University alumni clippings
  - Blood donations on behalf of Dr. Bailey., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    various notes and lists
  - Percival Bailey's book plate., undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Funeral directives for the family., 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    registration form filled out for Dr. and Mrs. Bailey with The Chicago Memorial Association; information sheets from the Association
  - Death certificate and certificate of cremation., 1973 August 10, 13 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Funeral and memorial service lists., 1973 August (Box 1, Folder 12)
    lists and notes prepared by Yevnigé Bailey (Mrs. Percival Bailey)
  - Funeral home register., 1973 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Memorial service., 1973 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    program of the service at First Congregational Church, Evanston, Illinois, with a statement of Dr. Bailey's personal credo; typescripts of eulogies by Drs. Roy R. Grinker, Sr., Paul C. Bucy, Joel Brumlik, Oscar Sugar, and Hajime Handa; group photographs
  - Death notices, obituaries, and published memorials., 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    signed published memorials: "The Anatomical Record" (by H.W. Magoun and C.D. Clemente); "Revista Española de Oto-Neuro-Oftalmologia y Neurocirugia" and "Archivos de Neurobiologia" (by Adolfo Ley); "Journal of Research and Training", Illinois Dept. Mental Health and and "The Psychiatric Examiner", Illinois Psychiatric Society (by R.R. Grinker, Sr.); "Biological Psychiatry) (by Paul C. Bucy); "Zeitschrift fu¨r Neurologie" (by G. Schaltenbrand); "Hoosharar", Armenian General Benevolent Union of America (by Arshalouise Bedrosian); "Ideggyogyaszati Szemle" (by Környey István); "Our Congregational Heritage" (by Dr. Bing)
  - Condolence cards and letters received by Yevnigé Bailey., 1973-1974; folder 1 of 5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    signed with first name only, or unidentifiable
  - Condolence cards and letters received by Yevnigé Bailey., 1973-1974; folder 2 of 5 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    A-C
  - Condolence cards and letters received by Yevnigé Bailey., 1973-1974; folder 3 of 5 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    D-J
  - Condolence cards and letters received by Yevnigé Bailey., 1973-1974; folder 4 of 5 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    K-O
  - Condolence cards and letters received by Yevnigé Bailey., 1973-1974; folder 5 of 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    P-Z
  - Letters from Dr. Paul C. Bucy to Yevnigé Bailey., 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters to Yevnigé Bailey., 1953, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Irene Anahid Bailey Freyer (1927-, daughter)., 1927-1956, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    letter to her mother, 1973; information on birth certificate; grade report; commencement program from Evanston Township High School, 1945, and diploma; Honors List for 1951 class from Syracuse University; ability and aptitude test scores
  - Norman Alishen Bailey (1931-, son)., 1949-1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    commencement program from Evanston Township High School, 1949; programs from high school and college drama productions and music recital; letter and a card to his father; ability and aptitude test scores
  - Gift to University of Chicago., 1950 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Acknowledgment of monetary gift
  - Miscellaneous family clippings and notes., 1952-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Clippings on politics, religion, science, entertainment, Armenia., 1953-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Honors and Awards, 1949-1983; Series 2.; 12 folders
  - Dr. Percival Bailey's 60th birthday celebration., 1952 May 30; folder 1 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    booklet dedicated "To Dr. Percival Bailey on the occasion of his sixtieth birthday, with the sincere affection, respect and admiration of his residents, pupils and friends": contains an appreciation by Dr. Paul C. Bucy, a copy of Dr. Bailey's curriculum vitae, society memberships, scholastic and professional honors and certificates, and a list of his residents and pupils; invitations to the Scientific Session and Luncheon in honor of Dr. Bailey at the University Club of Chicago, and to the Dinner at the South Shore Country Club, Chicago; program of the Scientific Session; typescript of remarks made by Dr. Georges Schaltenbrand; photograph of Drs. Alajouanine, Schaltenbrand, and Bailey shaking hands, signed by each
    items removed from scrapbook
  - Dr. Percival Bailey's 60th birthday celebration., 1952 May 30; folder 2 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    letters of congratulation
  - Dr. Percival Bailey's 60th birthday celebration., 1952 May 30; folder 3 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    cards and telegrams of congratulation; newspaper clippings
  - Dr. Percival Bailey's 60th birthday celebration., 1952 May 30; folder 4 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    leather-bound guestbook, signed by ca. 120 guests attending the dinner
  - Unveiling of Dr. Percival Bailey's portrait., 1957 October 5 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    typed draft and a printed copy of a booklet presented as a keepsake at the unveiling ceremony at University of Illinois College of Medicine; photographs of: the illustrations for Dr. Bailey's speech; Dr. Bailey viewing his portrait; Mrs. Bailey and the portrait; head shot of Edmund Giesbert, painter of the portrait, and Mr. Giesbert in a museum setting; Dr. Bailey and Mr. Giesbert; group photographs
  - Percival Bailey Lectures (Professor Percival Bailey Educational Project)., 1958, 1960-1969, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    list of donors to the Professor Percival Bailey Educational Project, 1958; invitations and speaker and/or group photographs for the Percival Bailey Lectures, given by his pupils and friends in his honor, for lectures no. 1-10, 1960-1969 (except for lecture nos. 8-9; invitation only for no. 10); reprint of "A tale of two drugs: urea and chymopapain", by Manucher J. Javid, M.D., the 1982 Percival Bailey Oration presented to the Central Neurosurgical Society, Chicago, 1982; a reprint from "Surgical Neurology" 18(4), Oct. 1982, of "Manucher J. Javid, M.D.", by Glenn A. Meyer, which mentions Dr. Bailey as his teachers and mentor; photograph of the Committee of the Percival Bailey Educational Project, second lecture, 1961: Rudy, Bailey, Sugar, Bucy, Klüver, Bashes, Grinker
    the Percival Bailey lecturers from 1960 on were: Dr. Lauretta Bender, Dr. Benjamin Pasamanick, Dr. Heinrich Klüver [because of Dr. Klüver's illness Dr. Ralph Gerard was the speaker], Dr. Curt P. Richter, Dr. Henri Baruk, Dr. Joel Elkes, D. Roger W. Sperry, Dr. Paul C. Bucy, no. 9 unknown, Dr. Henri Baruk
  - Dedication of the Percival Bailey Laboratories of Neuropsychology at Michael Reese Hospital and Medical Center, Chicago., 1968 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    cover letter from Dr. Roy R. Grinker, Sr., Director of the Psychosomatic and Psychiatric Institute at Michael Reese; news release from Michael Reese; newspaper clippings; two 8x10" photographs of Drs. Bailey and Grinker in the doorway of the Percival Bailey Laboratories, and a group at the reception
  - Gift to the University of Illinois Library of the Health Sciences, Chicago., 1974 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    program and proceedings of the dedication of the new building for the Library; "Medical Center News" story with photo of; typescript of Prof. Norman A. Bailey's comments on presenting Dr. Bailey's memorabilia to the library; correspondence; "A catalog of the Percival Bailey Collection of Neurology & Psychiatry", Chicago, 1973
    Dr. Bailey contributed memorabilia and over 700 volumes to the Library; some of his colleagues contributed funds for the production of the catalog
  - Lectureships., 1953-1962 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    McArthur Lecture, Chicago, 1953 - dinner guest list; D.J. Davis Lecture on Medical History, University of Illinois College of Medicine, 1962 - invitation
  - Academic honors., 1949-1963 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Docteur honoris causa, University of Paris, 1949; Doctor of Science, Southern Illinois University, 1952; Doctor of Science, University of Chicago, 1951; Distinguished Service Award, Medical Alumni, University of Chicago, 1957; Alumni Achievement Award, Southern Illinois University, 1958; Doctor of Laws, Chicago Medical School, 1963; Distinguished Professor of Neurology and Neurological Surgery, University of Illinois; Golden Apple award for outstanding teaching, University of Illinois College of Medicine; photograph of Dr. Bailey receiving an academic honor ["International College" is written on print, no further identification]
  - Professional society honors., 1953-1971 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    President, American Neurological Association, 1953; Honorary Fellow, North Pacific Society of Neurology and Psychiatry, 1953; Honorary Foreign Member, Association of British Neurologists, 1961; President, Illinois Psychiatric Society, 1954-1955, certificate awarded, 1970; Distinguished Service Award, The Society of Neurological Surgeons, 1971
    for a photo of the American Neurological Association officers, see Box 2, Folder XXXold 38
  - Other honors., 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    "Modern Medicine" Award for Distinguished Achievement, 1954; elected to National Academy of Sciences, 1955; Chevalier de la Légion d'Honneur de France, 1956
- Professional and Personal Writings, 1935-1972; Series 3.; 29 folders
  - Autobiographical accounts., 1966, undated; 23 p. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    typed pages (paged as p.36-58, covering ca. 1937-1966) of an autobiography focused mainly on travels, family vacations and doings, and other non-work-related activities [many of the pages parallel "South of the border", "West to the Rising Sun", and "An Armenian passa..."]; five-page "Chronicle of my life", a short chronological account, mostly of whereabouts and travels; short account of scientific interests; curriculum vitae - very sparse yearly account, 1892-1966
  - "South of the Border"., undated; 15 p. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    several drafts, typescript and manuscript
    account of a trip to Mexico City and countryside in 1944
  - "Haci Bektas Veli"., undated; 34 p. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    annotated typescript
    essay on Turkish/Armenian racial and cultural backgrounds and the importance of the Persian humanist and philosopher [known also as Haji Bektash Veli or Hajji Bektash Wali, ca. 1209-1271], on the development of a modern Turkey
  - "Needles, thimbles"., undated; 32 p. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    annotated typescript and some manuscript pages
    story of his wife's family's settling in the United States; note on first page: "merged with, or title changed to Albert Coffeegrounds, or First voyage of an Armenian Sinbad"
  - "Zeitoun"., 1935; 30 p. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Armenian history; read before the Chicago Literary Club, Oct. 21, 1935
  - "Sisvan"., 1940 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    typescript, read before the Chicago Literary Club, Jan. 8, 1940
    Armenian history; read before the Chicago Literary Club, Jan. 8, 1940
  - "Forty days of Musa Dagh"., 1945; 25 p. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    manuscript pages; letter from John Nuveen, Jr., to Dr. Bailey
    essay on Franz Werfel's novel "Die Vierzig Tage des Musa Dagh", published in 1933 and first translated into English in 1934; to quote Bailey, "This stirring novel is a better propaganda for the Armenian people than they have ever been able to devise for themselves."
  - "West to the Rising Sun"., 1950; 37 p. (Box 1, Folder 47)
    typescript
    essay about Dr. Bailey's weeks as an Expert Consultant to the U. S. Army Medical Corps in the Philippines and Japan in 1948; read before the Chicago Literary Club, Oct. 23, 1940; published in "Up from Little Egypt", 1969
  - "Pepper Pot"., 1952; 36 p. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    typescript, two versions
    some "illuminating anecdotes" of Dr. Bailey's interactions with Harvey William Cushing; read before the Chicago Literary Club, March 30, 1952
  - "M'sieu Bellay"., 1953, circa 1968; 30 p. (Box 1, Folder 49)
    typescript, two versions; three group photographs of student parties; two photos of left bank bookstalls, taken at a later date
    reminiscences about a year of medical study in Paris, 1921-1922; read before the Chicago Literary Club, Nov. 13, 1953; published in "Up from Little Egypt", 1969
  - "Der Herr Professor"., circa 1968; 30 p. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    essay about Dr. Bailey's 1932 sabbatical in Breslau, Germany, with Professor Otfrid Förster; read before the Chicago Literary Club, Oct. 4, 1954; published in "Up from Little Egypt", 1969
  - "Sister Ethelrita"., 1959; 28 p. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    essay on being a Surgical House Officer, Mercy Hospital, Chicago, 1918-1919; published in "Up from Little Egypt", 1969
  - "Ol Doc Artin", 1960; 35 p. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    typescript plus two manuscript pages
    memories of the home-town doctor; read before the Chicago Literary Club, Dec. 5, 1960; published in "Up from Little Egypt", 1969
  - "Ol Southern"., 1961; 37 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    partly an autobiographical account of early years and education, partly a historical account of the institutional changes Southern Teachers College underwent to become Southern Illinois University; essentially only the autobiographical part [first twenty pages] were read before the Chicago Literary Club, October 23, 1961 and published in "Up from Little Egypt", 1969
  - "A fantasied inaugural lesson: a brief account of my philosophy of psychiatry and how I derived it"., 1963; 33 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    annotated typescript, two versions
  - "Schöne Aussicht"., 1953; 31 p. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    typescript, three versions
    record of an automobile trip from Würzburg. Germany, to Lisbon, Portugal, with Dr. Georges Schaltenbrand (German neurologist), his wife and son, and Dr. Bailey and his wife and son in the party
  - "Janet and Freud"., 1955; 5 p. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    typescript of introduction to Dr. Bailey's Presidential Address to the Illinois Psychiatric Society, Chicago, May 8, 1955
    shortened version of the address was published in "Archives of Neurology and Psychiatry", 76(1): 76-89, 1956; Dr. Bailey studies with Pierre Janet in Paris, 1925-1926
  - "Thudichum - a search for the spirit"., 1958; 16 p. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    two typescripts
    essay on Johann Ludwig Wilhelm Thudichum's love of good wine, food and music [physician and biochemist, 1829-1901, who also wrote a treatise on viticulture and oenology]
  - "The seat of the soul"., 1959; 15 p. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    published in "Perspectives in Biology and Medicine", 1959, 2:417-441, 1959
  - Three lectures on Sigmund Freud., 1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    typescripts of: 1. "Story of a visionary who tried to be a scientist: Sigmund Freud, scientific period (1873-1897)" - read before the Armenian Academy of Sciences, Yerevan, Sep. 25, 1962; 2. "Sigmund Freud, 1873-1897: scientific period" - presented at Conference on Conditioning Therapy, Charlottesville, Virginia, April 13, 1962; 3. "Cryptic borrower", undated
  - "An Armenian pessa in the shadow of Ararat"., 1963; 17 p. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    three typescript versions, and a published version from "The Armenian Mirror-Spectator", 31(22), December 7, 1963; four snapshots: group in front of Armenian Hospital for Mentally Ill, Yerevan; Lake Sevan monastery; new homes in rural district outside Yerevan
    a description of the visit Dr. Bailey and his wife made to Yerevan, on the invitation of the Armenian Academy of Sciences to lecture to the All-Union Congress of Physiology
  - 18th Annual Address, Armenian Church Youth Organization., 1964 September 6 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    one page of handwritten notes
  - "Eulogium magistrorum meorum"., 1964-1965; 35 p. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    typescript; reprint; portrait photographs [mounted on cardboard] of Percival Bailey, Stella Orr (Bailey's mother), Charles Belva, Walter Upton (cousin), Gephart [also Gebhard] Bailey (uncle), Martha Buck (teacher), Henry William Shryock, Carlos Eben Allen, Harvey Carr, George W. Bartelmez, Julius Grinker, Harvey Cushing, Pierre Janet, Gaetan Gatian de Clérambault, and Johannes Gregorius Dusser de Barenne
    essay on the important mentors in Dr. Bailey's life; read before the Chicago Literary Club, April 20, 1965, and published in "Perspectives in Biology and Medicine", 1965, 8(1): 311-334; also published in "Up from Little Egypt", 1969
  - "Harun al-Rashid"., 1966; 32 p. (Box 2, Folder 14)